Guide to the Oliver F. Atkins photograph collection, 1943-1975
George Mason University Libraries
Special Collections and Archives, George Mason University
Oliver F. Atkins photograph collection
1943-1975
George Mason University. Special Collections and Archives.
Oliver F. Atkins, 1916-1977
C0036
59.5 linear ft.; 113 boxes
The Atkins collection consists of approximately 60,000 images that extensively document American political and cultural history from the 1940s through the 1970s. Most of the images that document American political life date from the early 1960s through the mid-1970s when Atkins worked as a photographer for the Saturday Evening Post and then later as the personal photographer to President Richard M. Nixon. The bulk of the American cultural documentation is from Atkins' work in the 1950s and early 1960s on specific stories for the Saturday Evening Post, and these stories cover other areas of the United States, particularly the Southeast up through the Northeast coast. There are also a number of international sets of images from Korea, Africa, and India. The collection consists largely of 8x10" and l3x10" color and black and white prints and 35mm and 4x5" black and white negatives. There are also a number of slides, contact sheets, and oversize mat prints. The collection also includes some correspondence and other documentation on Atkins' work and travel abroad.
Administrative Information
Alternative Form Available
Portions of the Atkins collection are available online through the Oliver F. Atkins Photograph Collection and the 1972 Richard Nixon Campaign Photographs.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Donated by Marjorie Atkins in 1978 and 1987.
Biographical Information
Oliver F. Atkins was born February 18, 1916 in Hyde Park, Massachusetts. He earned a B.A. in Journalism from the University of Alabama in 1938, and accepted a position with the Birmingham Post as a staff photographer. Within two years he became chief photographer for the Scripps Howard-owned paper. In 1940, he joined the Washington Daily News where he remained until 1942 and the outbreak of World War II. During the war, he served as a correspondent and photographer for the American Red Cross covering the African campaign, the invasions of Sicily, southern Italy, southern France, and Germany. After the war, Atkins joined the staff of the Saturday Evening Post. As the Washington correspondent for the Post, he photographed many important leaders of the United States and the world. Among them were Harry S Truman, Dwight D. Eisenhower, Richard M. Nixon, John F. Kennedy and Robert F. Kennedy, Martin Luther King, Jr., Winston Churchill, Gamel Nasser, Nikita Kruschev, Josip B. Tito, and Jawaharlal Nehru. He was the Post's Far East correspondent in 1951, and also enjoyed a personal and working relationship with the magazine's famous illustrator, Norman Rockwell.
In 1969, Atkins became the personal photographer of President Richard M. Nixon and chief White House photographer. Of his many images of Nixon, the series documenting the meeting of December 18, 1970 with Elvis Presley is the most famous and the most requested. After Nixon's resignation in 1974, Atkins became vice president of Curtis Publishing Company of Indianapolis and remained there until his death in 1977. Ollie Atkins's awards include the White House News Photographers' Association Grand Award, the Graflex All American Photo Contest Portrait Award, and the National Press Photographers' Association Personalities Award. Books by Ollie Atkins include Camera on Assignment (co-written with Charles Baptie, 1957), and The White House Years: Triumph and Tragedy (1977). He also contributed to William Safire's Eye on Nixon (1972).
Scope and Content
The Atkins collection consists of approximately 60,000 images that extensively document American political and cultural history from the 1940s through the 1970s. Most of the images that document American political life date from the early 1960s through the mid-1970s when Atkins worked as a photographer for the Saturday Evening Post and then later as the personal photographer to President Richard M. Nixon. The bulk of the American cultural documentation is from Atkins' work in the 1950s and early 1960s on specific stories for the Saturday Evening Post, and these stories cover other areas of the United States, particularly the Southeast up through the Northeast coast. There are also a number of international sets of images from Korea, Africa, and India. The collection consists largely of 8x10" and l3x10" color and black and white prints and 35mm and 4x5" black and white negatives. There are also a number of slides, contact sheets, and oversize matted prints. The collection also includes some correspondence and other documentation on Atkins' work and travel abroad.
Series 1 contains almost all of the prints in the collection. The prints document Atkins' positions as a photographer for the Saturday Evening Post and the personal photographer to President Richard M. Nixon. Many of the negatives of the prints in the first subseries can be found in Series 2 and 3. Subseries 1.1 consists largely of prints from Atkins work as a photographer for the Saturday Evening Post in Washington, D.C. There are also photographs from Saturday Evening Post stories that Atkins contributed to and those folders are labeled with the title of the article. The scope notes provide additional information about the subjects of the photographs and the locations when the folder titles are not descriptive enough. Subseries 1.2 consists of 8x10" prints from Atkins' work as the personal photographer to President Richard M. Nixon. The images document life in the White House, press conferences, visiting foreign leaders, presidential visits abroad, vacations, and Nixon's final days in office following his resignation. There are also numerous photographs of the Nixon's wife, Pat, and his daughters, Julie and Tricia. Most of the photographs are in color. Subseries 1.3 consists of both 8x10" and 11x14" prints arranged chronologically from Atkins' work as the personal photographer to President Richard M. Nixon. The prints cover much of the same subject matter as in subseries 1.2 and in some cases are duplicates. Most of the prints are black and white.
Series 2 contains 4x5" negatives created during Atkins's tenure as a photographer for the Saturday Evening Post, and most of the photographs are grouped together by story title. Some of the prints made from the negatives can be found in Subseries 1.1. Subjects include American political figures, such as Dwight D. Eisenhower, Alben W. Barkley, George Marshall, and Tom Connally; Washington, D.C., sites, such as the White House, the Library of Congress, and Howard University; and religious leaders, such as Ezra Taft Benson and Prophet Jones. Other subjects include American businessmen, military figures, and average citizens. Folder numbers refer to numbered "packets" containing multiple negatives of the same subject. Box 58 contains negatives other than 4x5" that could not be housed in the same containers. Some of these negatives are from the same stories and have the same packet numbering. Detailed caption descriptions for these packets can be found in Series 4.
Series 3 contains 35mm negatives, 4x5" negatives, contact sheets, and slides that Atkins created while he worked for the Saturday Evening Post in the 1950s and 1960s as well as some images from work he did during World War II. Prints from these images can be found in Series 1, and there are some copies of negatives that are in Series 4. Subseries 3.1 is arranged in chronological order and appears to be largely from Atkins' Washington File, a collection of images he maintained from various assignments. Subjects photographed during the early 1960s include the President John F. Kennedy and his cabinet, including Robert F. Kennedy; Jacqueline Kennedy; astronauts such as John Glenn and Alan Shepard; Senators and Representatives; protests and demonstrations such as the "March on Washington for Jobs and Freedom", with Martin Luther King, Jr.; and John F. Kennedy's inauguration and funeral. Subjects photographed during the mid-to-late 1960s include President Lyndon B. Johnson and his cabinet, including Robert S. McNamara and Dean Rusk; Nelson A. Rockefeller; Ladybird Johnson; Senators and Representatives; Malcolm X; the signing of the Civil Rights Bill with Martin Luther King, Jr.; astronauts Gus Grissom, John Young, and John Glenn; and protests and demonstrations, including the "Poor People's Campaign", with Jesse Jackson, Ralph Abernathy, and Coretta Scott King. Subseries 3.2 is arranged in alphabetical order. Subjects include Presidents Dwight D. Eisenhower, John F. Kennedy, and Lyndon B. Johnson, along with their cabinet members and families. Other political figures or events include United States Senators and Congressmen, such as Barry Goldwater, J. William Fulbright, and Margaret Chase Smith, and the Democratic and Republican National Conventions from 1956-1968. Other subjects include the Korean War and other overseas locales such as Africa, Cuba, India, New Zealand, and Yugoslavia; Washington, D.C., landmarks include the U.S. Capitol Building, the U.S. Supreme Court Building, the State Department Building, and the White House. As in Subseries 1.1 and Series 2, multiple folder titles are based on Saturday Evening Post story titles.
Series 4 contains correspondence, awards, press travel packets, copies of images for exhibits and reference use, and a photograph assignment on the Shenandoah Valley in Virginia. Of particular interest in the correspondence are letters between Atkins and the Saturday Evening Post about his work and other matters. Note that there is also correspondence and notes throughout the folders in the Series 3. The press packets document Nixon's travel abroad during his presidency and can be used in conjunction with the Nixon subject prints in Series 1. There are also publications that feature photographs by Atkins.
Series 5 contains mat photographs that span Atkins entire career from World War II to the White House. Subjects include World War II in Europe, the Korean War, and scenes from Africa, India, and the Middle East. Also pictured are American political figures such as Dwight D. Eisenhower, John F. Kennedy, Lyndon B. Johnson, and Richard M. Nixon. Other subjects include protests on the National Mall, landmarks in Washington, D.C., and New York City, coal miners, and Fidel Castro.
Arrangement
Organized into five series:
Series 1: Prints, 1943-1974 (Boxes 1-48)
Series 2: 4x5" Negatives, 1947-1956 (Boxes 49-57)
Series 3: Negatives, Contact Sheets, Slides, 1945-1975 (Boxes 58-101)
Series 4: Personal Papers, Exhibit Images, and Nature Photography, 1940s-1974 (Boxes 102-105, Oversize 13)
Series 5: Oversize, 1943-1971 (Oversize 1-12)
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Special Collections and Archives also holds many other photograph collections.
The National Archives and Records Administration holds the negatives and contact sheets of the images contained in Subseries 1.2 and 1.3.
Index Terms
Persons:
Acheson, Dean, 1893-1971--Photographs.; Alsop, Joseph, 1910-1989--Photographs.; Alsop, Stewart--Photographs.; Baker, Robert Gene--Photographs.; Cannon, Clarence, 1879-1964--Photographs.; Churchill, Winston, 1874-1965--Photographs.; Connally, Tom, 1877-1963--Photographs.; Derounian, Steven B. (Steven Boghos), 1918-2007--Photographs.; Douglas, Paul H. (Paul Howard), 1892-1976--Photographs.; Duke, Angier Biddle, 1915-1995--Photographs.; Eisenhower, Dwight D. (Dwight David), 1890-1969--Photographs.; Eisenhower, Julie Nixon--Photographs.; Eisenhower, Mamie Doud, 1896-1979--Photographs.; Ford, Gerald R., 1913-2006--Photographs.; Goldwater, Barry M. (Barry Morris), 1909-1998--Photographs.; Gore, Albert, 1907-1998---Photographs.; Hoffa, James R. (James Riddle), 1913---Photographs.; Johnson, Lady Bird, 1912-2007--Photographs.; Johnson, Lyndon B. (Lyndon Baines), 1908-1973--Photographs.; Kennedy, Edward M. (Edward Moore), 1932-2009--Photographs.; Kennedy, Ethel, 1928---Photographs.; Kennedy, John F. (John Fitzgerald), 1917-1963--Photographs.; Kennedy, Robert F., 1925-1968--Photographs.; Lewis, John L. (John Llewellyn), 1880-1969--Photographs.; Mansfield, Mike, 1903-2001--Photographs.; McCarran, Pat, 1876-1954--Photographs.; McCormack, John W., 1891-1980--Photographs.; McNamara, Robert S., 1916-2009--Photographs.; Meany, George, 1894-1980--Photographs.; Mesta, Perle, ca. 1890-1975--Photographs.; Mink, Patsy T., 1927-2002--Photographs.; Minoso, Minnie, 1922---Photographs.; Moyers, Bill D.--Photographs.; Muskie, Edmund S., 1914-1996--Photographs.; Nixon, Pat, 1912-1993--Photographs.; Nixon, Richard M. (Richard Milhous), 1913-1994--Photographs.; Nixon, Tricia--Photographs.; Olney, Warren, 1904-1978--Photographs.; Onassis, Jacqueline Kennedy, 1929-1994--Photographs.; Percy, Charles H., 1919---Photographs.; Reedy, George E., 1917-1999--Photographs.; Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich), 1908-1979--Photographs.; Romney, George W., 1907-1995--Photographs.; Rooney, John J., 1903-1975--Photographs.; Rusk, Dean, 1909-1994--Photographs.; Russell, Richard B. (Richard Brevard), 1897-1971--Photographs.; Sayre, Francis Bowes, 1915-2008--Photographs.; Scranton, William W. (William Warren), 1947---Photographs.; Symington, Stuart, 1901-1988--Photographs.; Taft, Robert, 1917-1993--Photographs.; Tree, Marietta, 1917-1991--Photographs.; Truman, Harry S., 1884-1972--Photographs.; Walker, Ernest P. (Ernest Pillsbury), 1891-1969--Photographs.; Whitehill, Arthur M. (Arthur Murray)--Photographs.; Woodruff, Robert Winship--Photographs.; Woods, Rose Mary--Photographs.
Corporate Names:
Ku Klux Klan (1915- )--Photographs.; Marriott Hot Shoppes--Photographs.; North Carolina (Battleship: BB-55)--Photographs.; Statler Hotel (Washington, D.C.)--Photographs.; Telegrafnoe agentstvo SSSR--Photographs.; Trinity Church (New York, N.Y.)--Photographs.; United States Capitol (Washington, D.C.)--Photographs.; United States. Air Force--Photographs.; United States. Government Printing Office--Photographs.; United States. Navy--Photographs.; United States. Postal Inspection Service--Photographs.; US Army Military Police School--Photographs.
Geographical Names:
Africa--Photographs.; India--Photographs.; Korea--Photographs.; Oval Office (White House, Washington, D.C.)--Photographs.; Reston (Va.)--Photographs.; Washington (D.C.)--Photographs.; White House (Washington, D.C.)--Photographs.
Subjects:
Agriculture--Photographs.; Coal miners--Photographs.; Cold weather clothing--Photographs.; Entomology--Photographs.; Fighter planes--Photographs.; Korean War, 1950-1953--Photographs.; Oyster industry--Chesapeake Bay (Md. and Va.)--Photographs.; United States--Politics and government--20th century--Photographs.; Presidents--Election--Photographs.; Sewing machines--Photographs.; Storage and moving trade--Photographs.; Submarines (Ships)--Photographs.; Unemployment--Photographs.
Document Types:
Aerial photographs.; Group portraits.; Legislative hearings.; Negatives.; Photographic prints.; Portraits.; Slides.
Contents List
- Series 1: Prints, 1943-1974; (48 boxes)
  Series 1 contains almost all of the prints in the collection. The prints document Atkins' positions as a photographer for the Saturday Evening Post and the personal photographer to President Richard M. Nixon. Many of the negatives of the prints in the first subseries can be found in Series 2 and 3.
  - Subseries 1.1: Subject, 1940s-1974; (15 boxes)
    This subseries consists largely of prints from Atkins work as a photographer for the Saturday Evening Post in Washington, D.C. There are also photographs from Saturday Evening Post stories that Atkins contributed to and those folders are labeled with the title of the article. The scope notes provide additional information about the subjects of the photographs and the locations when the folder titles are not descriptive enough.
    - Abernathy, Ralph, 1960s (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Acheson, Dean, March 1950 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Adventure of the moving men, April 1953 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Storage and moving trade in Washington, D.C.
    - Africa series, November-December 1960 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Guinea; Nigeria; South Africa
    - Ainus, the people who lost their tongues, August 1951 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Japan
    - Alsop, Stewart, 1960s (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Portraits with family
    - Alsop, Stewart, 1960s (Box 1, Folder 7)
      U.S. Navy; U.S. Air Force; fighter plane; Africa; agriculture; John F. Kennedy
    - The amazing Mr. Churchill, January 1952 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Winston Churchill, Harry Truman
    - Apollo 11, July 20, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Apollo 15, July 30, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Are we letting our children down, March 1950 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      School improvement programs in Arlington, Virginia
    - Are you letting your trees die?, September 1950 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      Entomology at Shenandoah National Park, Virginia
    - Atkins, Oliver, 1960s (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Oliver Atkins and Norman Rockwell
    - Atkins, Oliver, 1960s (Box 1, Folder 14)
      Oliver Atkins; Sid Caesar; Herbert Humphrey (autographed); Johnny Carson
    - Atkins, Oliver, August 12, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      Oliver Atkins and Gerald Ford
    - Atkins, Oliver, 1970s (Box 1, Folder 16)
      Portrait
    - Baker, Bobby, 1960s (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Bats are my best friends, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      Ernest P. Walker in Washington, D.C.
    - Battleships, November 1962 (Box 1, Folder 19)
      Includes negatives
    - Big Business wants only a few Generals, February 1955 (Box 1, Folder 20)
      American Machine & Foundry Company, New York City
    - Big noise from Nebraska, June 1950 (Box 1, Folder 21)
      Kenneth Wherry
    - Boy orator from Big Tussle, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 22)
      Carl Albert and family; Sam Ragburn; John McCormack; Harold Cooley; taken in Washington, D.C.
    - Bundy, McGeorge, 1960s (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Busiest Vice President we ever had!, July 1953 (Box 1, Folder 24)
      Richard M. Nixon in Washington, D.C.
    - Can Senator Taft win his biggest fight?, February 1950 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      Robert Taft in Canton, OH
    - Can we stop the Soviet subs?, July 1960 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      Washington, D.C.; Norfolk, Virginia; United States Navy
    - The case for Democrats, August 1952 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      Harry Truman; John Sparkman; Adlai Stevenson in Washington, D.C.
    - The case for Republicans, August 1953 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      Dwight D. Eisenhower in Boise, Idaho
    - Case of the nervous syllables, April 1957 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      Washington, D.C.; includes contact sheets
    - Castro, Fidel, 1950s (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Chase, Len, 1960s (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Church, Frank, 1960s (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Civil Rights, demonstrating at the White House, March 1965 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Civil Rights, march on Washington, D.C., August 1963 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Clark, Joseph S., 1950s (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Clark, Ramsey, 1960s (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Congress puts this show on the road, October 1952 (Box 2, Folder 13)
      Joint Senate and House recording facility; Charles B. Brownson; A.S. "Mike" Monroney, in Washington, D.C.
    - Congress verses the plunging neckline, November 1952 (Box 2, Folder 14)
      Mrs. Winfield Smart and family in Falls Church, Virginia
    - Congressional hearings, 1953-1956 (Box 2, Folder 15)
      Robert F. Kennedy; John McClellan; Harry Dexter White Case; Dave Beck; Gun control; Racketeering
    - The curious case of the Presidents' bathtubs, June 1952 (Box 2, Folder 16)
      Bathtubs, Washington, D.C.
    - Darnedest place in Washington, June 1950 (Box 2, Folder 17)
      Library of Congress; Luther Evans
    - Decline of Horatio Alger, September 1950 (Box 2, Folder 18)
      Boy reading, taken in Fairfax, Virginia
    - Deer, 1970s (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Democratic National Convention, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Democratic National Convention, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Demonstration for Israel in La Fayette Park, June 1967 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Desperate people at my door, December 1950 (Box 2, Folder 23)
      Unemployment, Washington, D.C.
    - That dizzy diplomatic whirl, April 1957 (Box 2, Folder 24)
      Ambassadors in Washington, D.C.
    - Dodd, Thomas J., 1950s (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Dogs, 1960s (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Don't junk the Marshall Plan yet!, March 1950 (Box 2, Folder 27)
      Portrait of Pat McCarran in Washington, D.C.
    - Dulles, John Foster, 1950s (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Eisenhower, Dwight, 1952-1956 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Eisenhower, Dwight, 1953-1954 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Elder Benson's going to catch it, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 2)
      Ezra Taft Benson; Hume, Virginia; Washington, D.C.
    - Ervin, Sam, 1960s (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - The feast of hungry shipbuilders, February 1957 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      Federal Maritime Administration; Washington, D.C.
    - Fidel Castro protest at White House, 1950s (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Ford, Gerald, August 9, 12, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 6)
      Julie and David Eisenhower; Alexander Haig; Ford family; Presidential swearing-in ceremony; Joint address to Congress
    - Fulbright, William J., 1960s (Box 3, Folder 7)
      Portraits
    - Furness, Betty, 1960s (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - George Mason College, 1960s (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - George Mason College dedication, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - George Mason College dedication, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Ghana, November 1960 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Gold at the end of Wall Street, August 1952 (Box 3, Folder 13)
      Battle Creek, Michigan; Delaware; New York City; Trinity Church
    - Goldwater, Barry, 1960s (Box 3, Folder 14)
      Betty Goldwater; William Miller; John McClellan
    - Guinea, November 1960 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Handy man with milk shake, September 1948 (Box 4, Folder 2)
      Marriott Hot Shoppe in Arlington, Virginia
    - The hard life of a new Congressman, June 1953 (Box 4, Folder 3)
      Steven Derounian; Andrews Air Force Base; Washington, D.C.; Mineola, New York
    - He licked the old man of the Senate, October 1951 (Box 4, Folder 4)
      Albert Gore and family in Carthage, Tennessee
    - He wants to keep Washington honest, August 1949 (Box 4, Folder 5)
      "Five percenters" investigation in Washington, D.C.
    - Headaches of a hotel keeper (parts 2 and 3), May 1950 (Box 4, Folder 6)
      Statler Hotel; Washington, D.C.; New York City; Boston
    - Here's what's behind Ike's grin, August 1952 (Box 4, Folder 7)
      Dwight D. Eisenhower; Marie Eisenhower; Chicago; New York City; Denver
    - Herter, Christian, 1950s-1960s (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Hoffa, James, 1950s-1960s (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Hoover, J. Edgar, 1950s-1960s (Box 4, Folder 10)
      portrait
    - How civil service is handcuffing Ike, June 1953 (Box 4, Folder 11)
      Washington, D.C.; McLean; Arlington, Virginia
    - How Harry Truman does his job, March 1949 (Box 4, Folder 12)
      Harry Truman; Fred Vinson; in Key West, Florida
    - How my hired man handles me, March 1953 (Box 4, Folder 13)
      Agriculture in Zirconia, North Carolina
    - How the Slovak underground fights, November 1951 (Box 4, Folder 14)
      Dr. V. Stefan Krajcovic in Washington, D.C.
    - Humphrey, Hubert H., 1960s (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - I saw us bungle defense agreements in Europe, September 28, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 16)
      Gordon W. Rule in Washington, D.C.
    - I say he's a wonderful guy, July 1952 (Box 4, Folder 17)
      Richard M. Nixon and family in Washington, D.C.
    - I'm guilty I built a modern house, January 1950 (Box 4, Folder 18)
      Modern movement (architecture); Washington, D.C.
    - India, 1950s (Box 4, Folder 19)